{"tossups": [{"question": "1. The biography Wrapped in Rainbows describes how this author pretended, at age 26, to be a teenager so she could get a free high school education. In an autobiographical essay, this author said her life offered no \u201cextenuating circumstances\u201d except that her \u201cgrandfather on the mother\u2019s side was not an Indian chief.\u201d An essay imagines waking up in this author\u2019s hometown and planting a marker in the ground designating this author (*) \u201cA Genius of the South.\u201d This author was given a Guggenheim Grant to study Jamaica and Haiti, providing material for her book Tell My Horse. The attempt to find the unmarked grave of this Eatonville-born author of \u201cHow it Feels to be Colored Me\u201d was described in an essay about \u201cLooking for\u201d her by Alice Walker. For 10 points, name this anthropologist who studied under Franz Boas, who also created Janie Crawford in Their Eyes Were Watching God.", "answer": "Zora Neale Hurston [prompt on \u201cLooking for Zora\u201d] &lt;WA, Authors/Bios&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Zora Neale Hurston &lt;WA, <b><u>Authors/Bios&gt;</u></b> [prompt on <u>Looking for Zora</u>]", "acceptable": ["Zora Neale Hurston &lt;WA, Authors/Bios&gt;", "Authors/Bios&gt;"], "promptable": ["Looking for Zora"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "2. In 1989, the Yomiuri Shimbun financed the \u201cThree Rivers\u201d expedition to this country, the first to uncover graves in areas protected by its Darkhad people. Nikolai Yadrintsev found a dragon monument in a ruin in this country known as the \u201cblack city\u201d or Kharbalgas. Several large sculptures of stone turtles are found outside a ruined capital city in this country whose \u201cPalace of Myriad Peace\u201d has yet to be found. The prince Kul Tigin is honored by 7th century inscriptions named for a river valley in this country\u2019s west, the (*) Orkhon, which was a power center for the Gokturk state. This country\u2019s oldest surviving Buddhist monastery, the Erdene Zuu monastery, was mutilated by its Communist leader Khorloogiin Choibalsan and is located in the medieval capital city of Karakorum. For 10 points, name this country, the homeland of an empire-builder named Temujin.", "answer": "Mongolia [or Mongol Uls] &lt;WA, Archaeology&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Mongolia &lt;WA, <b><u>Archaeology&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>Mongol Uls</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Mongolia &lt;WA, Archaeology&gt;", "Archaeology&gt;", "Mongol Uls"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "3. In a city named for one of these places, an attempt by police to crack down on Carnival celebrations led to the Canboulay riots. The \u201cfranchises, liberties, customs, and usages\u201d of several of these places were maintained by a Lord Warden created by Simon de Montfort. In a city named for one of these places, students staged a 1970 protest march to begin the Black Power Revolution, and the Red House was captured during a 1990 coup attempt by Jamaat al Muslimeen. Hastings, Hythe, Sandwich, New Romney, and a (*) fifth city formed a confederation named for the Norman term for five of these places. The Treaty of Nanking established five \u201ctreaty\u201d examples of these places, including Canton. Felixstowe is the busiest example of these places in the U.K. though Bristol, Dover, and Liverpool still see some traffic. For 10 points, identify this type of location which names the capital of Trinidad and Tobago.", "answer": "ports [or seaports; accept Port of Spain or Cinque Ports] &lt;WA, British/Other History&gt;", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>ports &lt;WA, British/Other History&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>seaports</u></b>; accept <b><u>Port of Spain</u></b> or <b><u>Cinque Ports</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["ports &lt;WA, British/Other History&gt;", "ports &lt;WA, British/Other History&gt;", "seaports", "Port of Spain", "Cinque Ports"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "These things are used to describe the life of a three-legged salesman in Mark Dunn\u2019s Ibid. In a novel, one of these things describes an author who obsessively watches [Jurassic Park] \u201clike a porno flick,\u201d while another relates a fear that a toilet\u2019s super-powerful suction will be used by a Hotel Manager for assassination. Some of these things were used to introduce the spoiled teenager Mona and the exacting tablemate Trudy. In another novel, these texts describe an escape via tunnel while notably neglecting the death of (*) Hazel. To \u201cmake the primary text an easier read,\u201d David Foster Wallace prolifically used these things within his essays. In a novel, the assassin Jakob Gradus is described in examples of these things written by a man who believes he is the escaped King of Zembla. For 10 points, identify these texts exemplified by Charles Kinbote\u2019s obsessive commentary on Shade\u2019s Pale Fire.", "answer": "footnotes [or endnotes, prompt on note or annotation] &lt;JC, Short Fiction&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>footnotes &lt;JC, Short Fiction&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>endnotes, prompt on note</u></b> or <b><u>annotation</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["footnotes &lt;JC, Short Fiction&gt;", "footnotes &lt;JC, Short Fiction&gt;", "endnotes, prompt on note", "annotation"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "5. Note to players: specific term required. An instance of this term refers to a September 23, 1868 action undertaken by Dr. Ram\u00f3n Emeterio Betances and Segundo Ruiz Belvis in the Puerto Rican town of Lares. This term describes the gathering of Andr\u00e9s Bonifacio\u2019s Katipuneros to tear up their cedula identification documents, which is said to have happened in either Balintawak or Pugadlawin. This term names an event that took place after Carlos Manuel de C\u00e9spedes issued the October 10th Manifesto, starting the Ten Years War in Cuba the day. A creek in modern day (*) S\u00e3o Paulo names one of these actions undertaken by Prince Pedro to sever ties with Portugal. One of these actions from 1810 is emulated annually on September 16 by crowds yelling \u201cMexicanos, viva M\u00e9xico!\u201d For 10 points, give this term applied to calls for independence in Portuguese and Spanish colonies, including one named for Ipiranga as well as an utterance by Father Hidalgo in Dolores.", "answer": "Cry [or cries; or Gritos; accept shouts; accept The Cry of Lares; accept The Cry of Balintawak or The Cry of Pugadlawin or The Cry of Yara or The Cry of Ipiranga or The Cry of Dolores; accept Grito de in place of \u201cCry of\u201d in any of the aforementioned answerlines; prompt on revolutions or uprisings or similar answers] &lt;AA, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Cry &lt;AA, World History&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>cries</u></b>; or <b><u>Gritos</u></b>; accept <b><u>shouts</u></b>; accept <b><u>The Cry of Lares</u></b>; accept <b><u>The Cry of Balintawak</u></b> or <b><u>The Cry of Pugadlawin</u></b> or <b><u>The Cry of Yara</u></b> or <b><u>The Cry of Ipiranga</u></b> or <b><u>The Cry of Dolores</u></b>; accept <b><u>Grito de</u></b> in place of \u201cCry of\u201d in any of the aforementioned answerlines; prompt on <u>revolutions</u> or <u>uprisings</u> or <u>similar answers</u>]", "acceptable": ["Cry &lt;AA, World History&gt;", "Cry &lt;AA, World History&gt;", "cries", "Gritos", "shouts", "The Cry of Lares", "The Cry of Balintawak", "The Cry of Pugadlawin", "The Cry of Yara", "The Cry of Ipiranga", "The Cry of Dolores", "Grito de"], "promptable": ["revolutions", "uprisings", "similar answers"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "6. A family in this book count themselves lucky for never having to open the pages for gonorrhea or syphilis in their used up copy of Dr. Gunn\u2019s Family Medicine. A short chapter in this novel discusses the life of Olive, a woman loosely based on the author\u2019s mother, who sold so many liberty bonds during World War I that she received a free airplane ride. A woman in this novel drowns herself by forcibly holding her head down in a shallow pond, shortly after contracting syphilis from her wooden (*) legged husband. After being severely beaten, a woman who had earlier faked her death with chicken blood arrives at the doorstep of a farmhouse in Salinas Valley in this novel. That character, Cathy Ames, runs away to work at Madam Faye's brothel after giving birth to Caleb and Aron. For 10 points, name this retelling of the Cain and Abel story based on three generations of the Trask family, a novel by John Steinbeck.", "answer": "East of Eden &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>East of Eden &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;</u></b>", "acceptable": ["East of Eden &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "East of Eden &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Though actually a Wednesday, a 1916 event that was the greatest natural disaster of World War I was called \u201c[this color] Friday.\u201d A published book known as the \u201c[this color] Book\u201d made the case for Germany\u2019s lack of fault in starting World War I. This was the only color of the German Empire\u2019s flag that changed when it transitioned to the Weimar Republic. Erich von Falkenhayn\u2019s purported objective for the Battle of Verdun was to (*) \u201cbleed France\u201d this color. In a movement named after an object of this color, British men in civilian garb were accused of cowardice by women presenting them with a feather of this color. A faction named for this color was supported by a \u201cPolar Bear Expedition\u201d that landed at Arkhangelsk in 1918. For 10 points, what color names the Russian faction that opposed the Bolsheviks?", "answer": "white [or White Friday; or White Book; accept white feather] &lt;AA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>white &lt;AA, Continental History&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>White Friday</u></b>; or <b><u>White Book</u></b>; accept <b><u>white feather</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["white &lt;AA, Continental History&gt;", "white &lt;AA, Continental History&gt;", "White Friday", "White Book", "white feather"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "8. Jean Baudrillard\u2019s book about this non-Gulf War event accuses one group of \u201cbring[ing] about an excess of reality\u201d and \u201cplay[ing] the game...solely with the aim of disrupting it.\u201d In one philosopher\u2019s book Rogues, this event \u201cmedia-theatricalized\u201d the globalization-driven loss of distinction between state and non-state actors. A book asking \u201cWas there an alternative?\u201d in responding to this event was written by Noam Chomsky. This event was called \u201cthe first historic world event in the strictest sense\u201d due to a \u201cuniversal eyewitness\u201d in an interview by Giovanna Borradori of (*) Jacques Derrida and Jurgen Habermas. Both Noam Chomsky and Ron Paul re-popularized the term \u201cblowback\u201d to explain the origins of this event engineered by Mohammed Atta. For 10 points, name this event that was the subject of the Amiri Baraka poem \u201cSomebody Blew Up America\u201d and the \u201cFalling Man\u201d photograph.", "answer": "9/11 attacks [or the terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001; be generous on accepting descriptions like attack on the Twin Towers or the World Trade Center] &lt;AA, Phil/SS&gt;", "category": "Social Science", "subcategory": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>9/11 attacks &lt;AA, Phil/SS&gt;</u></b> [or the <b><u>terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001</u></b>; be generous on accepting descriptions like attack on the Twin Towers or the World Trade Center]", "acceptable": ["9/11 attacks &lt;AA, Phil/SS&gt;", "9/11 attacks &lt;AA, Phil/SS&gt;", "terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "9. In a poem, this character\u2019s monologue anticipates an audience\u2019s possible criticism of him before describing the \u201cconjurer\u2019s profession\u201d of writing. This character compares God to a freshwater fish attempting to escape to salt water; he also argues there is no afterlife because God \u201cdoth His worst in this our life.\u201d An essay about this character, who speaks last in Auden\u2019s \u201cThe Sea and the Mirror,\u201d compares \u201clettered\u201d and \u201cunlettered\u201d cultures; that essay by Stephen Greenblatt is (*) \u201cLearning to Curse.\u201d This character, who eats food that he calls \u201cscamels,\u201d demands to be called X in a post-colonialist play by Aime Cesaire. In the play he first appears in, this character enters the service of Stephano and Trinculo, and is the son of a sorceress who worships Setebos. For 10 points, name this son of Sycorax and slave of Prospero in Shakespeare\u2019s The Tempest.", "answer": "Caliban &lt;JC, Drama&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Caliban &lt;JC, Drama&gt;</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Caliban &lt;JC, Drama&gt;", "Caliban &lt;JC, Drama&gt;"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "10. This document enjoins the people it concerns to \u201clabor faithfully for reasonable wages\u201d in \u201call cases allowed.\u201d Richard Hofstadter mockingly stated that this document had \u201call the moral grandeur of a bill of lading.\u201d The preliminary version of this document was promulgated four months after its author rebuked David Hunter for creating a similar document following action at Fort Pulaski, and a month after its author wrote an open reply to a letter titled (*) \u201cThe Prayer of Twenty Millions.\u201d The signing of this document \u201cfive score years ago\u201d is referenced in Martin Luther King\u2019s \u201cI Have a Dream\u201d speech. This document did not apply to Maryland, Missouri, Delaware, or Kentucky. For 10 points, Abraham Lincoln freed Southern slaves by issuing what document?", "answer": "Emancipation Proclamation &lt;WA, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Emancipation Proclamation &lt;WA, US History&gt;</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Emancipation Proclamation &lt;WA, US History&gt;", "Emancipation Proclamation &lt;WA, US History&gt;"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "11. In a novel by Jules Verne, a revolutionary disguised as the physician Dr. Antikertt returns to help free his friends who are trying to liberate this country. A literary journal from this country birthed its Nyugat generation of writers. An author born here created a prisoner who hears Bogrov repeatedly whisper his name after he has been violently dragged through the prison floor and left for dead. In a novel set in this country, a Doctor watches the frantic anxiety that sets over Mr. Schmidt and (*) Futaki after they learn that their co-worker Iremias is not actually dead. An author from here wrote about the fourteen year old, Gyorgy Kovacs, who is taken to Auschwitz and Buchenwald before finally becoming a laborer at the Zeitz concentration camp in his novel Fatelessness. For 10 points name this birthplace of Arthur Koestler, home to Laszlo Krasznahorkai and Imre Kertesz.", "answer": "Hungary [or Magyarorszag] &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Hungary &lt;SB, <b><u>LongFic&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>Magyarorszag</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Hungary &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "LongFic&gt;", "Magyarorszag"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "12. Eugenia Tognotti posited that this event heralded the end of the \u201cscientific triumphalism\u201d of Richard Pfeiffer. John Martin Poyer won a Navy Cross for preventing this event from affecting American Samoa. Geoffrey Rice\u2019s Black November demonstrated a path for this outbreak via the merchant ship Mantua, which was also the subject of a John M. Barry history. Humphries et al posited that this outbreak was made worse by the CLC, which may have moved it to Devonport and Plymouth during its \u201cSecond Wave.\u201d This outbreak jumped to the U.S. via (*) Fort Riley, Kansas. This outbreak, made worse by the fact that its causative agent could induce encephalitis lethargica and cytokine storms, originally got its name because of the lack of wartime censorship in a nation ruled by King Alfonso XIII. For 10 points, identify this pandemic in which an H1N1 strain killed 5% of the world\u2019s population", "answer": "1918 flu pandemic [or Spanish flu; or La Grippe; accept answers that indicate the first major outbreak of influenza; prompt on \u201cinfluenza\u201d or \u201cinfluenza epidemic\u201d or \u201cinfluenza pandemic\u201d; do not accept \u201caffluenza\u201d] &lt;EM, Historiography&gt;", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>1918 flu pandemic &lt;EM, Historiography&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>Spanish flu</u></b>; or <b><u>La Grippe</u></b>; accept <b><u>answers that indicate the first major outbreak of influenza</u></b>; prompt on <u>influenza</u> or <u>influenza epidemic</u> or <u>influenza pandemic</u>; do not accept \"affluenza\"]", "acceptable": ["1918 flu pandemic &lt;EM, Historiography&gt;", "1918 flu pandemic &lt;EM, Historiography&gt;", "Spanish flu", "La Grippe", "answers that indicate the first major outbreak of influenza"], "promptable": ["influenza", "influenza epidemic", "influenza pandemic"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "At the demands of a Senate, two sisters co-ruled this polity for seven weeks before one of them carried out a coup and married a man known by an epithet meaning \u201che who fights alone.\u201d A female regent of this polity used her son\u2019s marriage to a mistress as an excuse to blind her son, having earlier tried to marry him to a daughter of Hildegard of the Vinzgau. Customs of cloistering women are noted in the latter of two texts from this polity called the Strategikon. Otto III married a princess from this polity, (*) Theophanu. Many did not consider Charlemagne\u2019s coronation a usurpation partly because, at the time, this polity was ruled by a woman named Irene. A princess from this empire recorded interactions with Bohemond of Taranto, Robert Guiscard, and other Normans in the Alexiad. For 10 points, name this empire whose luminaries included Anna Comnena and Empress Theodora.", "answer": "Byzantine Empire [or Eastern Roman Empire or Basileion ton Romaion or Byzantium; prompt on Roman Empire or Romaioi or Rum; definitely don\u2019t take \u201cSultanate of Rum\u201d though!] &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Byzantine Empire &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>Eastern Roman Empire</u></b> or <b><u>Basileion ton Romaion</u></b> or <b><u>Byzantium</u></b>; prompt on <u>Roman Empire</u> or <u>Romaioi</u> or <u>Rum</u>; definitely don\u2019t take \u201cSultanate of Rum\u201d though!]", "acceptable": ["Byzantine Empire &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;", "Byzantine Empire &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;", "Eastern Roman Empire", "Basileion ton Romaion", "Byzantium"], "promptable": ["Roman Empire", "Romaioi", "Rum"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "14. The sixth stanza of one poem imagines that the \u201cdaughters\u201d of this animal \u201ccan share / something of every paddler\u2019s heritage.\u201d A poem consisting of observations made during the \u201cnineteenth autumn\u201d says of these animals \u201cTheir hearts have not grown old / Passion or conquest, wander where they will.\u201d A poem titled for this animal takes the form of a Shakespearean sonnet for the first eight lines and a Petrarchan sonnet for the last six; that poem\u2019s eleventh line is split in two halves after its tenth, which mentions (*) \u201cthe broken wall, the burning roof and tower.\u201d A \u201cshudder in the loins\u201d due to one of these animals is described in that poem, which speaks of the \u201cindifferent beak\u201d of one of them. The speaker meditates upon his age in a poem that observes \u201cnine and fifty\u201d of these animals at Coole. For 10 points, name this bird which, in a W. B. Yeats poem, seduces Leda.", "answer": "swans [accept \u201cThe Wild Swans at Coole\u201d or \u201cLeda and the Swan\u201d] &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>swans &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;</u></b> [accept <b><u>The Wild Swans at Coole</u></b> or <b><u>Leda</u></b> or the <b><u>Swan</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["swans &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "swans &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "The Wild Swans at Coole", "Leda", "Swan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "15. Note to players: we want the form that these works take. Many of the most important British works in this form were almost lost in the 1731 Cotton Fire at Ashburnham House; the saved works later became the original British Museum collection. Lillian Randall argued that conflicts with the Lombards are depicted in these works as knights fighting snails. 113 unidentified plant species appear in an as-yet (*) undeciphered document in this form named after a Polish collector. Eadfrith adapted St. Jerome\u2019s Vulgate into one of these documents called the Lindisfarne Gospels, an exemplar of these documents\u2019 Hiberno-Saxon style, which is also used in the Book of Kells. For 10 points, name these documents written by monks that were often \u201cilluminated\u201d with fanciful hand-drawn illustrations prior to the invention of the printing press.", "answer": "illuminated manuscripts [prompt on books or codex or codices or scrolls or psalters or book(s) of hours by asking \u201cwhat type of book/codex/scroll/psalter/book of hours?\u201d; do not accept or prompt on any answer pertaining to \u201cprinted\u201d books] &lt;AA, Historical Sources&gt;", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>illuminated manuscripts &lt;AA, Historical Sources&gt;</u></b> [prompt on <u>books</u> or <u>codex</u> or <u>codices</u> or <u>scrolls</u> or <u>psalters</u> or <u>book(s) of hours</u> by asking \u201cwhat type of book/codex/scroll/psalter/book of hours?; do not accept or prompt on \"any answer pertaining to \u201cprinted\u201d books\"]", "acceptable": ["illuminated manuscripts &lt;AA, Historical Sources&gt;", "illuminated manuscripts &lt;AA, Historical Sources&gt;"], "promptable": ["books", "codex", "codices", "scrolls", "psalters", "book(s) of hours"], "rejectable": ["any answer pertaining to \u201cprinted\u201d books"], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "16. A 2013 book by Michael Emmerich notes how, in the late 19th century, a parodic \u201crustic\u201d version of this novel by a \u201cfalse\u201d author became extremely popular due to movable type. The third of the re-translations of this novel by the author of Quicksand uses one-third more words than the original in updating its language. Several dramatic treatises cite characters from this novel with the nicknames \u201cevening face\u201d and \u201cfloating boat\u201d as paragons of grace. The laconic 1976 translation of this novel by (*) Edward Seidensticker contrasts with its first full English one, a loose rendition by Arthur Waley. Its final chapter provides the title of a 1959 short story in which a man romances his stepmother, titled \u201cThe Bridge of Dreams.\u201d The first novel in world history is often considered to be, for 10 points, what novel that contains the blank chapter \u201cVanished Into the Clouds,\u201d a work by Murasaki Shikibu?", "answer": "The Tale of Genji &lt;WA, Literary Legacy&gt;", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "The <b><u>Tale of Genji &lt;WA, Literary Legacy&gt;</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Tale of Genji &lt;WA, Literary Legacy&gt;", "Tale of Genji &lt;WA, Literary Legacy&gt;"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "17. A poem about this sport begins with the exclamation \u201cHallelujah! It works. We blew the shit out of them\u201d and ends with the speaker asking a lover to \u201ccome over here and kiss me on the mouth.\u201d This sport, which titles a Harold Pinter poem, is also the sport of choice of Herb Wallagher, who stops playing it after becoming paralyzed following a waterskiing accident in Richard Ford\u2019s The Sportswriter. A former player of this sport named Roberta (*) Muldoon becomes a bodyguard for Jenny Fields after transitioning genders in A World According to Garp. Taft Robinson and Gary Harkness play this sport for Logos College in a Don Delillo novel tangentially named for it. For 10 points, name the sport that is focused on in the novel, End Zone.", "answer": "American football [or gridiron football; prompt on football] &lt;SB, Miscellaneous Lit&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>American football &lt;SB, Miscellaneous Lit&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>gridiron football</u></b>; prompt on <u>football</u>]", "acceptable": ["American football &lt;SB, Miscellaneous Lit&gt;", "American football &lt;SB, Miscellaneous Lit&gt;", "gridiron football"], "promptable": ["football"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "18. Strabo notes a number of conflations between people living in this region and the Getae to the north, such as a class of ascetics called the kapnobatai. Many smaller kingdoms within this region were united by Sitalces and his descendants into the Odrysian kingdom. Coastal cities of this region and in Paeonia were the sources of the most skilled peltasts in the Hellenistic world. Recurring motifs of horse-riding divinities in this region\u2019s rock art often represent a god that this region shared with Phrygia named (*) Sabazios. In antiquity, Miltiades the Elder governed a peninsula known as this region\u2019s \u201cChersonese.\u201d In the Third Servile War, a number of Gallic gladiators such as Gannicus and Crixus allied with a gladiator from this region, Spartacus. Diomedes and Orpheus were thought to be from, for 10 points, what ancient region corresponding to the eastern Balkans?", "answer": "Thrace [prompt on Balkans; accept Mysia and prompt on Asia Minor before \u201cOdrysian\u201d] &lt;WA, Ancient History&gt;", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Thrace &lt;WA, Ancient <b><u>History&gt;</u></b> [prompt on <u>Balkans</u>; accept <b><u>Mysia</u></b> or <b><u>prompt on Asia Minor</u></b> before \u201cOdrysian]", "acceptable": ["Thrace &lt;WA, Ancient History&gt;", "History&gt;", "Mysia", "prompt on Asia Minor"], "promptable": ["Balkans"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "19. A W. Montgomery Watt book in this genre titled for a \u201cstatesman\u201d combines his two previous efforts in this genre, published in 1953 and 1956. Karen Armstrong has written two books in this genre, one of which formed the basis of a PBS series. Work in this genre produced in the 20th century, but still regarded as authoritative, include a work drawing on \u201cthe earliest sources\u201d by Martin Lings, as well as The Sealed Nectar. Works in this genre comprise the body of s\u012bra literature, as exemplified by the efforts of Ibn Ishaq, whose work was used by (*) al-Tabari as a primary source. Though not scripture, almost all of these works relate events such as the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah, the execution of the Qurayza, the Night of Power, and the Night Journey. For 10 points, identify this genre of works which depict the life of the founder of Islam.", "answer": "biographies of Muhammad [accept sira before \u201csira\u201d; prompt on biography or biographies by asking \u201cof whom?] &lt;WA, HistInLit&gt;", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>biographies of Muhammad &lt;WA, HistInLit&gt;</u></b> [accept <b><u>sira</u></b> before \u201csira; prompt on <u>biography</u> or <u>biographies</u> by asking \u201cof whom?]", "acceptable": ["biographies of Muhammad &lt;WA, HistInLit&gt;", "biographies of Muhammad &lt;WA, HistInLit&gt;", "sira"], "promptable": ["biography", "biographies"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "20. This essay describes the \u201ccurious feeling\u201d of thinking one is watching \u201csome kind of dummy\u201d when hearing a speech about standing \u201cshoulder to shoulder\u201d with others. This essay asserts that a writer \u201cis not really thinking\u201d when confusing images, as in the phrase \u201cthe jackboot is thrown into the melting pot.\u201d Near its end, this essay advises \u201cBreak any of these rules sooner than saying anything outright barbarous,\u201d which is among six rules for (*) writers it posits. It demonstrates a point by using the words \u201cObjective considerations of contemporary phenomena\u201d to open a re-translation of a passage of Ecclesiastes. This essay argues against the use of \u201cdying metaphors\u201d and \u201cpretentious diction\u201d and articulates attitudes towards speech its author earlier explored in Homage to Catalonia. For 10 points, name this George Orwell essay arguing against abuses of his native tongue.", "answer": "\u201cPolitics and the English Language\u201d &lt;WA, Essays/Crit&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\u201cPolitics and the English Language\u201d &lt;WA, Essays/Crit&gt;</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\u201cPolitics and the English Language\u201d &lt;WA, Essays/Crit&gt;", "\u201cPolitics and the English Language\u201d &lt;WA, Essays/Crit&gt;"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "21. This activist profiled the first head of the federal Children\u2019s Bureau in the biography My Friend, Julia Lathrop. This activist and Josephine Lowell chartered the National Consumers League to protect employees. In \u201cNewer Ideals of Peace,\u201d this activist attacked proponents of so-called \u201cnegative\u201d peace and promoted a peace platform she carried into the conference Women at The Hague, from which she emerged as president of Women\u2019s International League for Peace and Freedom. Herbert Hoover appointed this activist to disburse aid to civilians from the former Central Powers, an experience recounted in the memoir (*) Peace and Bread in Time of War. This activist drew inspiration from a visit to London\u2019s Toynbee Hall. She was the first American woman to win the Nobel Peace Prize, partly for founding a Chicago social settlement with Ellen Gates Starr in 1889. For 10 points, name this American social worker who founded Hull House.", "answer": "Jane Addams &lt;AA, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Jane Addams &lt;AA, US History&gt;</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Jane Addams &lt;AA, US History&gt;", "Jane Addams &lt;AA, US History&gt;"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "22. Before a fight, Muhammad Ali collaborated with this poet to pen a \u201cPoem on the Annihilation of Ernie Terrell.\u201d The speaker of a poem by this author exclaims \u201cAssign Yogi Berra to Cape Canaveral; he could handle any missile.\u201d In that poem, the speaker argues that \u201cYou can never tell with either / how it will go / or what you will do\u201d while discussing the relationship between sports and (*) poetry. She wrote that the title subject of another of her poems will not have been written \u201ctill the autocrats\u201d among\u00a0us can be \u201c\u2018literalists of the imagination\u2019\u201d or until \u201cimaginary gardens with real toads\u201d have formed. That poem, which was shortened to just three lines in the 1967 edition of her Complete Poems, begins with the declaration, \u201cI, too, dislike it.\u201d For 10 points, name this Modernist author of the poem, \u201cPoetry.\u201d", "answer": "Marianne Moore &lt;SB, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Marianne Moore &lt;SB, Poetry&gt;</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Marianne Moore &lt;SB, Poetry&gt;", "Marianne Moore &lt;SB, Poetry&gt;"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "23. The Musgum people built fortified towns to repulse raiders from polities east of this body of water, such as the Bagirmi kingdom. Carriers of the typically Western European haplogroup R1b migrated to a \u201cMega\u201d version of this body of water during the Holocene, whose disappearance is one factor that explains a \u201cpump\u201d theory of migrations. Long, flat-bottomed boats were built for use on this body of water by the greatest mai of the Sayfawa dynasty, (*) Idris Alooma. The Transqua Project has proposed redirecting the Ubangi river to reverse damage to this body of water, along which the Bornu empire flourished. This body of water in the Sahel region shrank by 95% from 1960 to 2007. For 10 points, name this body of water which shares its name with a country governed from N\u2019djamena.", "answer": "Lake Chad [accept Megachad] &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "category": "Geography", "subcategory": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Lake Chad &lt;WA, World History&gt;</u></b> [accept <b><u>Megachad</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Lake Chad &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "Lake Chad &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "Megachad"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "24. Gayatri Spivak\u2019s essay \u201cIn Praise of a Friend\u201d is dedicated to this author. After drinking a banned ancient drink, a character in a novel by this author confesses his love for Mukami, who committed suicide because her father did not approve of their love. A one-legged character created by this author makes a living by reselling items seized from a garbage pile on his donkey cart, takes care of the orphan Joseph, and leads a (*) march to confront his district's member of parliament. This author created a fictional city where surveyors planning to create a Trans-African Highway die in a plane crash. That city, Ilmorog, is home to the Theng\u2019eta Brewery where Chui, Kimeria and Mzigo burned to death. In a novel that borrows its title from a Derek Walcott poem, this author wrote of Karega, who burns down the brothel where Wanja works. For 10 points, name this author of Petals of Blood.", "answer": "Ngugi wa Thiong\u2019o [or James Ngugi] &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Ngugi wa Thiong\u2019o &lt;SB, <b><u>LongFic&gt;</u></b> [or <b><u>James Ngugi</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Ngugi wa Thiong\u2019o &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "LongFic&gt;", "James Ngugi"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}